<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>git-rm</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="source">Git</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="version"></refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">Git Manual</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
  <refname>git-rm</refname>
  <refpurpose>Remove files from the working tree and from the index</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id="_synopsis">
<literallayout><emphasis>git rm</emphasis> [-f | --force] [-n] [-r] [--cached] [--ignore-unmatch]
          [--quiet] [--pathspec-from-file=&lt;file&gt; [--pathspec-file-nul]]
          [--] [&lt;pathspec&gt;&#8230;]</literallayout>
<simpara></simpara>
</refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1 id="_description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Remove files matching pathspec from the index, or from the working tree
and the index. <literal>git rm</literal> will not remove a file from just your working
directory. (There is no option to remove a file only from the working
tree and yet keep it in the index; use <literal>/bin/rm</literal> if you want to do
that.) The files being removed have to be identical to the tip of the
branch, and no updates to their contents can be staged in the index,
though that default behavior can be overridden with the <literal>-f</literal> option.
When <literal>--cached</literal> is given, the staged content has to
match either the tip of the branch or the file on disk,
allowing the file to be removed from just the index. When
sparse-checkouts are in use (see <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-sparse-checkout</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>),
<literal>git rm</literal> will only remove paths within the sparse-checkout patterns.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;pathspec&gt;&#8230;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Files to remove.  A leading directory name (e.g. <literal>dir</literal> to remove
        <literal>dir/file1</literal> and <literal>dir/file2</literal>) can be given to remove all files in
        the directory, and recursively all sub-directories, but this
        requires the <literal>-r</literal> option to be explicitly given.
</simpara>
<simpara>The command removes only the paths that are known to Git.</simpara>
<simpara>File globbing matches across directory boundaries.  Thus, given two
directories <literal>d</literal> and <literal>d2</literal>, there is a difference between using
<literal>git rm 'd*'</literal> and <literal>git rm 'd/*'</literal>, as the former will also remove all
of directory <literal>d2</literal>.</simpara>
<simpara>For more details, see the <emphasis>pathspec</emphasis> entry in <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>gitglossary</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-f
</term>
<term>
--force
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Override the up-to-date check.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-n
</term>
<term>
--dry-run
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Don&#8217;t actually remove any file(s).  Instead, just show
        if they exist in the index and would otherwise be removed
        by the command.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-r
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Allow recursive removal when a leading directory name is
        given.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        This option can be used to separate command-line options from
        the list of files, (useful when filenames might be mistaken
        for command-line options).
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--cached
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Use this option to unstage and remove paths only from the index.
        Working tree files, whether modified or not, will be
        left alone.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--ignore-unmatch
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Exit with a zero status even if no files matched.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--sparse
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Allow updating index entries outside of the sparse-checkout cone.
        Normally, <literal>git rm</literal> refuses to update index entries whose paths do
        not fit within the sparse-checkout cone. See
        <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-sparse-checkout</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> for more.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-q
</term>
<term>
--quiet
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        <literal>git rm</literal> normally outputs one line (in the form of an <literal>rm</literal> command)
        for each file removed. This option suppresses that output.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--pathspec-from-file=&lt;file&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Pathspec is passed in <literal>&lt;file&gt;</literal> instead of commandline args. If
        <literal>&lt;file&gt;</literal> is exactly <literal>-</literal> then standard input is used. Pathspec
        elements are separated by LF or CR/LF. Pathspec elements can be
        quoted as explained for the configuration variable <literal>core.quotePath</literal>
        (see <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-config</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>). See also <literal>--pathspec-file-nul</literal> and
        global <literal>--literal-pathspecs</literal>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--pathspec-file-nul
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Only meaningful with <literal>--pathspec-from-file</literal>. Pathspec elements are
        separated with NUL character and all other characters are taken
        literally (including newlines and quotes).
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_removing_files_that_have_disappeared_from_the_filesystem">
<title>REMOVING FILES THAT HAVE DISAPPEARED FROM THE FILESYSTEM</title>
<simpara>There is no option for <literal>git rm</literal> to remove from the index only
the paths that have disappeared from the filesystem. However,
depending on the use case, there are several ways that can be
done.</simpara>
<refsect2 id="_using_8220_git_commit_a_8221">
<title>Using &#8220;git commit -a&#8221;</title>
<simpara>If you intend that your next commit should record all modifications
of tracked files in the working tree and record all removals of
files that have been removed from the working tree with <literal>rm</literal>
(as opposed to <literal>git rm</literal>), use <literal>git commit -a</literal>, as it will
automatically notice and record all removals.  You can also have a
similar effect without committing by using <literal>git add -u</literal>.</simpara>
</refsect2>
<refsect2 id="_using_8220_git_add_a_8221">
<title>Using &#8220;git add -A&#8221;</title>
<simpara>When accepting a new code drop for a vendor branch, you probably
want to record both the removal of paths and additions of new paths
as well as modifications of existing paths.</simpara>
<simpara>Typically you would first remove all tracked files from the working
tree using this command:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">git ls-files -z | xargs -0 rm -f</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
<simpara>and then untar the new code in the working tree. Alternately
you could <emphasis>rsync</emphasis> the changes into the working tree.</simpara>
<simpara>After that, the easiest way to record all removals, additions, and
modifications in the working tree is:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">git add -A</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
<simpara>See <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-add</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry>.</simpara>
</refsect2>
<refsect2 id="_other_ways">
<title>Other ways</title>
<simpara>If all you really want to do is to remove from the index the files
that are no longer present in the working tree (perhaps because
your working tree is dirty so that you cannot use <literal>git commit -a</literal>),
use the following command:</simpara>
<literallayout class="monospaced">git diff --name-only --diff-filter=D -z | xargs -0 git rm --cached</literallayout><simpara></simpara>
</refsect2>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_submodules">
<title>SUBMODULES</title>
<simpara>Only submodules using a gitfile (which means they were cloned
with a Git version 1.7.8 or newer) will be removed from the work
tree, as their repository lives inside the .git directory of the
superproject. If a submodule (or one of those nested inside it)
still uses a .git directory, <literal>git rm</literal> will move the submodules
git directory into the superprojects git directory to protect
the submodule&#8217;s history. If it exists the submodule.&lt;name&gt; section
in the <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>gitmodules</refentrytitle><manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> file will also be removed and that file
will be staged (unless --cached or -n are used).</simpara>
<simpara>A submodule is considered up to date when the HEAD is the same as
recorded in the index, no tracked files are modified and no untracked
files that aren&#8217;t ignored are present in the submodules work tree.
Ignored files are deemed expendable and won&#8217;t stop a submodule&#8217;s work
tree from being removed.</simpara>
<simpara>If you only want to remove the local checkout of a submodule from your
work tree without committing the removal, use <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-submodule</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> <literal>deinit</literal>
instead. Also see <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>gitsubmodules</refentrytitle><manvolnum>7</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> for details on submodule removal.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_examples">
<title>EXAMPLES</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<literal>git rm Documentation/\*.txt</literal>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Removes all <literal>*.txt</literal> files from the index that are under the
        <literal>Documentation</literal> directory and any of its subdirectories.
</simpara>
<simpara>Note that the asterisk <literal>*</literal> is quoted from the shell in this
example; this lets Git, and not the shell, expand the pathnames
of files and subdirectories under the <literal>Documentation/</literal> directory.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
<literal>git rm -f git-*.sh</literal>
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Because this example lets the shell expand the asterisk
        (i.e. you are listing the files explicitly), it
        does not remove <literal>subdir/git-foo.sh</literal>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_bugs">
<title>BUGS</title>
<simpara>Each time a superproject update removes a populated submodule
(e.g. when switching between commits before and after the removal) a
stale submodule checkout will remain in the old location. Removing the
old directory is only safe when it uses a gitfile, as otherwise the
history of the submodule will be deleted too. This step will be
obsolete when recursive submodule update has been implemented.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_see_also">
<title>SEE ALSO</title>
<simpara><citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-add</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry></simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> suite</simpara>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
