<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE refentry PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<?asciidoc-toc?>
<?asciidoc-numbered?>
<refentry>
<refmeta>
<refentrytitle>git-mailinfo</refentrytitle>
<manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
<refmiscinfo class="source">Git</refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="version"></refmiscinfo>
<refmiscinfo class="manual">Git Manual</refmiscinfo>
</refmeta>
<refnamediv>
  <refname>git-mailinfo</refname>
  <refpurpose>Extracts patch and authorship from a single e-mail message</refpurpose>
</refnamediv>
<refsynopsisdiv id="_synopsis">
<literallayout><emphasis>git mailinfo</emphasis> [-k|-b] [-u | --encoding=&lt;encoding&gt; | -n]
               [--[no-]scissors] [--quoted-cr=&lt;action&gt;]
               &lt;msg&gt; &lt;patch&gt;</literallayout>
<simpara></simpara>
</refsynopsisdiv>
<refsect1 id="_description">
<title>DESCRIPTION</title>
<simpara>Reads a single e-mail message from the standard input, and
writes the commit log message in &lt;msg&gt; file, and the patches in
&lt;patch&gt; file.  The author name, e-mail and e-mail subject are
written out to the standard output to be used by <emphasis>git am</emphasis>
to create a commit.  It is usually not necessary to use this
command directly.  See <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git-am</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> instead.</simpara>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_options">
<title>OPTIONS</title>
<variablelist>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-k
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Usually the program removes email cruft from the Subject:
        header line to extract the title line for the commit log
        message.  This option prevents this munging, and is most
        useful when used to read back <emphasis>git format-patch -k</emphasis> output.
</simpara>
<simpara>Specifically, the following are removed until none of them remain:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Leading and trailing whitespace.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Leading <literal>Re:</literal>, <literal>re:</literal>, and <literal>:</literal>.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
Leading bracketed strings (between <literal>[</literal> and <literal>]</literal>, usually
        <literal>[PATCH]</literal>).
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>Finally, runs of whitespace are normalized to a single ASCII space
character.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-b
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        When -k is not in effect, all leading strings bracketed with <emphasis>[</emphasis>
        and <emphasis>]</emphasis> pairs are stripped.  This option limits the stripping to
        only the pairs whose bracketed string contains the word "PATCH".
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-u
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The commit log message, author name and author email are
        taken from the e-mail, and after minimally decoding MIME
        transfer encoding, re-coded in the charset specified by
        <literal>i18n.commitEncoding</literal> (defaulting to UTF-8) by transliterating
        them.  This used to be optional but now it is the default.
</simpara>
<simpara>Note that the patch is always used as-is without charset
conversion, even with this flag.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--encoding=&lt;encoding&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Similar to -u.  But when re-coding, the charset specified here is
        used instead of the one specified by <literal>i18n.commitEncoding</literal> or UTF-8.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-n
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Disable all charset re-coding of the metadata.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
-m
</term>
<term>
--message-id
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Copy the Message-ID header at the end of the commit message.  This
        is useful in order to associate commits with mailing list discussions.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--scissors
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Remove everything in body before a scissors line (e.g. "-- &gt;8 --").
        The line represents scissors and perforation marks, and is used to
        request the reader to cut the message at that line.  If that line
        appears in the body of the message before the patch, everything
        before it (including the scissors line itself) is ignored when
        this option is used.
</simpara>
<simpara>This is useful if you want to begin your message in a discussion thread
with comments and suggestions on the message you are responding to, and to
conclude it with a patch submission, separating the discussion and the
beginning of the proposed commit log message with a scissors line.</simpara>
<simpara>This can be enabled by default with the configuration option mailinfo.scissors.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--no-scissors
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Ignore scissors lines. Useful for overriding mailinfo.scissors settings.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
--quoted-cr=&lt;action&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        Action when processes email messages sent with base64 or
        quoted-printable encoding, and the decoded lines end with a CRLF
        instead of a simple LF.
</simpara>
<simpara>The valid actions are:</simpara>
<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<literal>nowarn</literal>: Git will do nothing when such a CRLF is found.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<literal>warn</literal>: Git will issue a warning for each message if such a CRLF is
        found.
</simpara>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<simpara>
<literal>strip</literal>: Git will convert those CRLF to LF.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
<simpara>The default action could be set by configuration option <literal>mailinfo.quotedCR</literal>.
If no such configuration option has been set, <literal>warn</literal> will be used.</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;msg&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The commit log message extracted from e-mail, usually
        except the title line which comes from e-mail Subject.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
<varlistentry>
<term>
&lt;patch&gt;
</term>
<listitem>
<simpara>
        The patch extracted from e-mail.
</simpara>
</listitem>
</varlistentry>
</variablelist>
</refsect1>
<refsect1 id="_git">
<title>GIT</title>
<simpara>Part of the <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>git</refentrytitle><manvolnum>1</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> suite</simpara>
</refsect1>
</refentry>
